Guide to the Francis Griffith Newlands Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Topical files, 1869 - 1936; Series II
  - Waterways
    - Inland Waterways Commission, 1907 (Box 74, Folder 753-757)
  - World War I
    - Speech, 1917 (Box 74, Folder 758)
    - Printed material, 1915-1917 (Box 74, Folder 759-762)
  - Miscellanea
    - Budget, 1910-1913 (Box 75, Folder 763)
    - Budget committee, 1910-1913 (Box 75, Folder 764)
    - Chevy Chase Land Co., 1936 (Box 75, Folder 765)
    - Chicago Trust Conference, 1899 (Box 75, Folder 766)
    - Democratic League of California, 1879-1885 (Box 75, Folder 767)
    - Education: printed materia1, 1916-1917 (Box 75, Folder 768)
    - Finance: printed material, 1898-1917 (Box 75, Folder 769)
    - Ledger, 1899-1900 (Box 75, Folder 770)
    - Legislative Reference Bureau, 1911-1913 (Box 75, Folder 771)
    - Lewis and Clark Centennial Commemorative Diploma, 1905 (Box 79)
      Presented to Francis Newlands for distinguished service.
    - Maps
      - "Map Showing the Territorial Apportionment of Appropriations Under the Newlands-Broussard River Regulation Bill", Undated (Box 79)
        Two copies.
      - "Map of the Sacramento Valley from Chico Landing to Suisun Bay, Shows Plan of Improvement for Solution of Flooding in Valley", 1904 (Box 79)
      - Contour maps of unregulated river basin and regulated river basin, Undated (Box 79)
      - "Submerged Dikes, Staggered Dikes and Cellulated Fascines for Ripraping the Bends of Rivers," by David Neale, 1907 September 16 (Box 79)
      - "Yosemite National Park Showing Changes in Boundaries", Circa 1890 (Box 79)
      - "Approximate Position of Mining Property and Quartz Mills Situated Tributary to the Colorado River Between Needles Cal. and El Dorado, Nev", Undated (Box 79)
      - "Phoenix and Additions", Undated (Box 79)
    - Merchant Marine, 1915-1917 (Box 75, Folder 772)
    - Nevada, 1899-1917 (Box 76, Folder 773)
    - Newlands, Francis G., 1869-1914 (Box 76, Folder 774-775)
    - Oriental and Negro, 1907-1912 (Box 76, Folder 776)
    - Peace, 1910-1917 (Box 76, Folder 777)
    - Photographs and negatives, undated (Box 76, Folder 778-779)
    - Power plant, 1916 (Box 76, Folder 780-782)
    - Printed material, 1900-1916 (Box 77, Folder 782-785)
    - Public health, 1911-1913 (Box 77, Folder 786)
    - Public improvements, 1899-1914 (Box 77, Folder 787)
    - Receipts, 1872-1874 (Box 77, Folder 788)
    - San Francisco, 1907-1916 (Box 77, Folder 789)
    - Taxation, 1899 (Box 77, Folder 790)
    - Titanic, 1912 (Box 78, Folder 791)
    - War claims, 1896-1900 (Box 78, Folder 792)
    - Washington, D.C., 1895-1900 (Box 78, Folder 793)
    - General, undated (Box 78, Folder 794-795)
- Scrapbooks [microfilm], 1887-1918; Series III
  The scrapbooks in this series contain information on many topics with which Newlands was associated during his life. The original scrapbooks were microfilmed for preservation purposes, and then discarded. Patrons must use microfilm HM 132.
  - Index to Scrapbook No. 5, Public works, Nevada commercial and irrigation, 1887 June 26 - 1894 October 25 (Reel 1)
  - Index to Scrapbook No. 6, Nevada commercial and irrigation, 1890 February 10- 1893 August 26 (Reel 1)
  - Nevada local politics, 1898 December 6 - 1899 January 31 (Reel 1)
  - Nevada political and irrigation, reclamation and Cuban annexation, 1900 August 28 - 1902 August 21 (Reel 1)
  - 1900 Campaign, Irrigation, 1898-1900 (Reel 1)
  - Nevada local politics, 1898 October 10 - 1899 April 19 (Reel 1)
  - Nevada political campaign, 1906 July 3 - 1912 October 23 (Reel 2)
  - Campaign 1904, National and state history of reclamation, 1904 June 13 - October 31 (Reel 2)
  - Campaign 1904-1906, History of Reclamation Act, Smythe's editorials, 1904 April 2 - October 23, 1906 March 23 - November 16 (Reel 2)
  - 1908 Nevada campaign (Reel 2)
  - Political campaigns, 1908 Sep1 - October 12 (Reel 3)
  - Political campaigns in Nevada, 1908 October 13 - November 6 (Reel 3)
  - Program of legislation, 1911 - 1912 (Reel 3)
  - Political campaigns in Nevada, 1909-1911 (Reel 4)
  - Political, 1912 (Reel 4)
  - Nevada campaign, 1912-1914 (Reel 5)
  - Nevada political matters, 1913 - 1916 (Reel 5)
  - Presidential candidacy, 1904 - 1912 (Reel 6)
  - National politics, 1911 - 1916 (Reel 6)
  - Railway legislation - national incorporation, 1904 December 13 - 1908 October 28 (Reel 6)
  - Railroad legislation, 1908 - 1918 (Reel 6)
  - Railroad legislation, 1914 December - 1917 January 13 (Reel 7)
  - Railroad strike, 1916 August (Reel 7)
  - Amendment to Erdman Act (Reel 7)
  - Labor Adamson Act, 1916 (Reel 7)
  - Joint Congressional committee, 1915 November - 1916 August (Reel 7)
  - Joint Congressional committee, 1916 December 1 - 1918 (Reel 8)
  - Joint Congressional committee, 1916 August- December (Reel 8)
  - Irrigation, Reclamation, Cuba, Campaign of 1902, 1901 January 27 - 1902 December 30 (Reel 8)
  - Irrigation, Reclamation, and Campaign of 1902, 1902 August 25 - 1903 November 22 (Reel 8)
  - Loose clippings concerning irrigation (Reel 8)
  - Irrigation, 1902 - 1911 (Reel 9)
  - Irrigation, Reclamation laws and work, Truckee Carson project, National Irrigation Congress, 1910 September - 1916 October 1 (Reel 9)
  - Waterways and flood control, 1889 - 1917 (Reel 9)
  - Waterways, 1907-1909 (Reel 10)
  - Waterways, river regulation, flood control, 1910 January 1 - 1912 December 31 (Reel 10)
  - Waterways, river regulation, flood control, 1913-1914 (Reel 11)
  - Waterways and flood control, 1913 June 20 - 1916 April 1 (Reel 12)
  - Financial, 1903 August 18 - 1913 December 25 (Reel 12)
  - Interstate Trade Commission, Newlands Bill, 1908 - 1912 (Reel 12)
  - Tariff, 1913-1914 (Reel 12)
  - Foreign relations and national defense, 1914 - 1917 (Reel 13)
  - Cuban affairs, 1895 - 1906 (Reel 13)
  - Philippine junket, 1905 August 1 - September 4 (Reel 13)
  - Visit of Congressional delegation to Manila, 1905 (Reel 13)
  - Miscellany, 1902 - 1906 (Reel 13)
  - Race problems--Negro, Chinese, Japanese, 1903 - 1914 (Reel 13)
  - Nevada local matters, 1907 - 1918 (Reel 14)
  - Nevada (Reel 14)
  - Material found at end of scrapbook (Reel 14)
  - President's speeches, 1909 September 16 - 1912 September 25 (Reel 14)
  - Roosevelt's speeches, 1910 September 17 - 1912 September 28 (Reel 14)
  - Wilson's speeches (Reel 15)
  - Miscellany, including Currency, Merchant marine, Tariff, Trust legislation, Philippines, 1890-1917 (Reel 15)
  - Death of Senator Newlands, Eulogies - successor, 1917 December 25 - 1918 February 2 (Reel 15)
  - Newlands' speeches and documents, 1910-1913 (Reel 15)
- Additonal materials, 1871-1921; Accession 2009-M-028
  The bulk of this accession comprises over 600 personal letters to and from the Newlands family members, including members of the Charles Johnston family, Washington, D.C. (Two daughters of Francis Newlands married two sons of the Johnston family.) Financial files, photographs, and topical files are included, listed alphabetically by topic, and chronologically by year therein.
  - Correspondence between Newlands family members
    - 1888 1888 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1889 1889 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1892 1892 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1894 1894 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - 1895 1895 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1896 1896 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - 1897 1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1898 1898 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1899 1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1900 1900 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - 1900 1900 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - 1901 1901 (Box 2, Folder 7-11)
      Includes letter to Edythe Newlands from Lyman Gage, written during his term as U. S. Secretary of the Treasury.
    - 1902 1902 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
    - 1903 1903 (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
    - 1904 1904 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - 1905 1905 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - 1906 1906 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1907 1907 (Box 5, Folder 8-12)
    - 1907 1907 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - 1908 1908 (Box 6, Folder 4-7)
    - 1909 1909 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 1910 1910 (Box 6, Folder 9-11)
    - 1911 1911 (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
    - 1912 1912 (Box 7, Folder 8-10)
    - 1912 1912 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Undated Undated (Box 8, Folder 3-6)
    - Loose envelopes, 1900-1910 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence between Francis G. Newlands, J. C. Kirkpatrick, and others, 1908 September 22-1913 December 29, undated (Box 9, Folder 1-12)
      Regarding the rebuilding of the Palace Hotel after the 1906 San Francisco earthquake.
  - Finances
    Turn of the century billhead invoices and receipts of Johnston family expenses, Washington, DC, listed chronologically, with cancelled checks and bankbooks last.
    - 1875-1900 1875-1900 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1901 1901 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1902 1902 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1906 1906 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
    - 1907 1907 (Box 10, Folder 6-9)
    - 1908 1908 (Box 10, Folder 10-13)
    - 1908 1908 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1909 1909 (Box 11, Folder 2-5)
    - 1910 1910 (Box 11, Folder 6-9)
    - 1910 1910 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 1911 1911 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1912 1912 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 1913-1916 1913-1916 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 1917-1918 1917-1918 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - 1919-1921 1919-1921 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Undated Undated (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
    - Cancelled checks and bankbooks, 1905-1919 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of Francis Newlands and family members, Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Topical files
    - Annexation of the Republic of Hawaii to the United States, 1898 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Letter to Edythe Newlands containing an invitation to ceremony and Citizens Guard ribbon. (President McKinley signed the "Newlands Resolution," named after Senator Francis Newlands, on July 7, 1898, to officially annex Hawaii to the United States.)
    - Book of Common Prayer, 1893 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Contains marriage certificate of Edythe Marion Newlands and Charles Haven Ladd Johnston, 1903 April 14.
    - Chevy Chase library dedication, Maryland, Circa 1890s (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Acquisition of land due in part to efforts of Senator Francis Newlands and others.
    - Congressional publications of Senator Newlands's remarks, 1911-1913 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Essays and notes on Italian artists and writers, 1910, undated (Box 13, Folder 6-7)
      Handwritten in Italian.
    - Fairmont Hotel floor plan, San Francisco, Circa 1906-1907 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Jackson Day Banquet, Reno, Nevada, 1910 January 8, 1912 January 8 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      Remarks of Senator Newlands to Nevada Democratic State Central Committee.
    - Land deeds and patent letters, 1871-1883, 1907-1908, 1917 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Miscellanea, notes, receipts, 1880-1911, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Newlands genealogy, 1897 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Newspaper clippings of a politcal nature, 1908-1912 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Occidental Land and Improvement Company, 1906 July 13, 28 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      Re status of certain land in Fresno and Merced area.
    - Oregon and California R. R. Co., 1878 January 29 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Oregon Steam Ship Company, 1878 January 29 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Overland Limited, 1913 November 7, 10 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Palace Hotel valuation and statistics, 1911-1918 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Panama-Pacific Exposition, 1910 August 30, October 3 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - River Regulation Committee, 1912 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Senator Francis G. Newlands: His Work, 1908 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      Compiled by M. F. Hudson